There's something I've been saying on
this channel for a very long time now.
And the more time that passes and the
more traders I've spoken to over the
years, the more and more convinced I am
that this is absolutely true. Here's the
thing. When you identify a problem with
your trading, whether it's something
that's stopping you from progressing to
the next level or harming your
performance in some way, and there are
many problems and many common ones that
traders experience that often those are
just the symptom level problems. And
those are the things that everyone's
spending their time and attention trying
to solve and fix and overcome. But just
like anything, if you treat the symptom
without actually finding out the cause
and treating that, you're not really
going to get very far. And with all of
these problems, when you dig deep to
find out what the root cause is, there's
usually just a handful of them that are
behind most of the problems that traders
experience. And one of those root cause
problems that come up time and time
again is about people's perception of
what trading is, what they should be
doing, what they shouldn't be doing,
what the aim of all of it is. And I
think that a lot of traders need a
complete perspective change to
understand trading in a completely
different way that will therefore set
them on a much better path to maybe
succeeding at this cuz let's face it,
most traders are failing and to at least
feel like they understand what they're
doing. So, in this video and in the next
couple of videos, I want to walk you
through a series of mental shifts that
you can make that will change the way
that you look at trading and set you on
that much better path. And to a certain
extent, these different mental shifts
are all interconnected. So, I want you
to look at them as being one overall
thing. And these are topics, they're the
kind of things that I usually get a lot
of push back on where people say, "Oh,
no, that's not right." Because it's
different to what they've been told for
the years before that they've been
learning to trade. All I ask of you for
this video and the next ones is that you
keep an open mind and try your best to
understand what it is that I'm really
telling you and don't just make a
judgment from one thing and say, "No,
that's different to what I understand,
so I'm not going to listen." Because
what tends to happen is that when we
release these sorts of videos where it's
about some sort of paradigm shift in
some way, then later down the line, we
start seeing it appearing on other
people's channels. people email us later
down the line saying that at the time I
didn't understand what you're saying or
it didn't resonate with me but now it's
really helpful and I think that if you
just keep an open mind you'll maybe see
what I'm trying to explain to you and I
really think it will have a good impact
on your trading. Now just quickly before
I share my screen and we get started I
just want to say for any regular viewers
of the channel I'm sorry that I haven't
posted in such a long time. I think it's
like 6 months since our last video. I
didn't intend for it to be that long,
but I just got busy with other things
like my own trading, uh, different
projects, our community, and so on. But
during that time, I still did send out
training videos and different things
like that to our newsletter. So, if you
want to make sure you don't miss out on
anything, the link is in the description
box. It's free to sign up, and that way
you can receive more training insights.
And also I'll be starting again my end
of week email, Nicholas's notes, where
within that email, I also put out a
video or a post breaking down some of my
trades from that week. So if you want to
stay on top of what trades I'm taking
and have more shorter insights in that
email, then that's where you need to
sign up and that way you don't miss out
on anything. Although I'm hoping it's
not going to be another 6 months before
I release a video. Hopefully just a
matter of days. Let's see. Famous last
words. So in today's session and like I
said it is part of like you can think of
it as a series. I want to talk about the
concept of intentional statements and
here's what I mean by that. So you can
see it on screen there that every time
you take an action or make a decision in
the markets you're making an implicit
statement. So you're implying something
through your actions. Actions speak
louder than words. When you put your
money behind something then you are
saying something about the thing that
you're putting money behind. And when
you make adjustments to that in some
way, you're also saying something. But
think of it outside of the context of
trading. If you're putting your money
behind something, what is it that you're
making a statement about in that
situation? So, we are making these
implicit statements. But most traders
don't realize what statement they're
actually making. And if they knew the
statement they were making through their
actions, through their decisions, they
wouldn't necessarily agree with those
statements. And so, of course, this
leads to unintended consequences. And
there's something I've talked about
before on this channel, but I want to
bring it up again because I think it's
relevant here that I think about with
any activity, not just trading, but you
can think about different sports,
different, I don't know, games,
activities, hobbies that everything can
fall on this sort of scale, this
continuum if you want to call it that.
And it's the luck skill continuum or
skill luck continuum. And we can think
about everything, every activity as
falling somewhere on this scale. So for
example, if we think about playing, I
don't know, roulette, if you didn't have
technology that tells you where the
ball's going to land, which do exist,
those those different types of
technology, it's going to be all the way
down here, 100% luck, right? And if we
think about something like chess at a
high level, you don't win a game of
chess like when it's grand masters
playing against each other. They're not
winning by luck. It's based on skill,
strategy. It's almost entirely up here.
And so we can think about different
activities falling somewhere along here.
And the thing about trading is that it
can be all the way down here 100% luck
because we all know that people can jump
into the markets, take trades completely
ram randomly, just basically gambling
like what most new traders do and
therefore it's entirely luck cuz they
don't know what they're doing. But
actually, surprisingly, I'd say most
traders fall in this area here. maybe
not as far this way, but somewhere in
this area. Because although they think
they're doing something meaningful, they
think they're analyzing something that's
meaningful in the markets, they think
their strategy is meaningful, actually
the way they're trading is no better
than just flipping a coin. It's all like
false causality, clustering illusions,
and things like that that make them
think the thing they're seeing is
actually going to be predictive in some
way, and it's not. And so what we're
trying to do as traders is to move as
far as we can this way. But we have to
always understand that we can never go
100% at the skill side because the
markets are out of our control. We can
control what we do, but we can't control
what the market does. So we can never
say it's 100% skill because there's
always an element of luck. Because
another way to think about this is
rather than it being luck and skill, we
can say that it's things that we can't
control.
and things that we can control.
So, we can control our actions. We can't
control the markets. So, we can never
get all the way over here. We can get as
close as we possibly can. Now, here's
the thing. If you're making statements
with your actions that you you don't
realize you're making or you think
you're making a different statement,
then obviously you're taking actions or
doing things that are no longer in your
control. So rather than us moving this
way with things that we can control,
we're actually moving this way because
we aren't fully in control of the the
actions we're taking or we're in control
of the actions we're taking but not in
control of what we're meaning by those
actions and what we're intending by
them. And so there are unintended
consequences because there's an element
of luck to it. And so if you want to
trade better, you need to be aware of
the actual statements you're making and
you need to make sure that your
statements are intentional. And when you
look at great traders, whether they
realize it or not, they get really good
at expressing their analysis in the
right way, that they end up making the
right statements through their actions.
And I think this is part of many skills
that there are two broad categories. You
have the part that most people pay
attention to, which is whether you can
actually execute the skill, like can I
do a tennis serve the way it's meant to
be done? And then you've got the part of
actually being able to know when to use
the skill and how to use the skill. So,
I don't just want to serve in tennis and
get it in the right area. I'm also
trying to direct my opponent in a
certain way. Like, you always hear about
uh sportsmen and women who get to the
end of their career where they've got a
bit older and their body's failing them
and they often talk about this moment
where they can see what they need to do,
but their body just doesn't respond in
the way that they want it to. So, they
can see the skill they're meant to to be
executing, but then they can't execute
it. And with beginners in lots of skills
and sports, it's the opposite. They
execute something but don't know what
they're doing. So, think about if you
don't know anything about chess, you
know where the pieces are meant to move,
like how the pieces move, but you don't
really know about strategies or things
like that. Well, if you're playing
against someone who knows what they're
doing, you might make a move and they're
reading what you're doing and thinking,
"Ah, they're they're trying to do this.
This is the statement they're making
when you could just be doing it randomly
because you have no idea what you're
doing." Okay? So we have to keep this in
mind in trading especially because it is
a skill that involves strategy and it's
a complex skill with lots of different
subsets of the skill that we need to or
a whole skill set that we need to
develop that these things are critical
for actually succeeding. So, let me
explain a bit further what I mean by
implicit statements. And you can get
used to my questionable visuals here
because I'm going to end up doing these
like flow diagram mind map type things
from now on. And that means that it's up
to me to put in all these random stupid
things. So, what do I mean by implicit
statements? So, I think a good way to
think about this is to imagine someone
who knows nothing about you. So, that's
why I've got the alien here. Imagine an
alien arrives on Earth. They've been
studying human behavior and culture and
the things we do for decades and now
they're here to understand more about
us. And so the alien comes and knocks on
your door and says, "Hey, can I come in
and try and phone home?" And while he's
busy doing that, you say, "Look, this is
what I've just been doing with my
analysis in the markets since you're
interested. I've just taken this action.
What do you think I'm implying by this?
Like what do you think my belief is
about the market by taking this action?"
And the alien not having the bias that
you have in your mind and the statements
and the understanding you have in your
mind will purely look at the logic of
the actions and tell you well if you're
doing this in this situation surely that
means that you think this about the
market. And so for most traders,
whatever that sort of objective view of
the logic of the actions would be is not
necessarily what they're intending
because unfortunately most traders just
take actions in the markets, make
decisions without truly thinking through
the logic behind them. And it's often
because of things that they've been
taught and things that are around the
trading industry that because people
have repeated the same thing so many
times, everyone assumes that that's the
way that's done and that's what that
action means. But it's not necessarily
the case. You see this whole, let's call
it like a ecosystem or microcosm, this
trading industry, it's a race to
simplicity that the more simple you can
make something sound, the easier you can
make something for someone to pick up
very quickly, the more people are going
to follow your stuff and learn with you.
And so it's a race to having things
being as simple as possible. But simple
isn't always correct. And in fact, in
this case, a lot of the time simple is
not correct. So people boil things down
to simple rules and simple actions that
every trader should be taking in certain
situations that are often illogical. And
when you break it down by thinking, hold
on a second though, what statement am I
actually making? You realize it's
illogical. And that's when you set
yourself on a path to doing things much
better where you can control the
situation, control your actions, and
lead to more intended consequences. Now,
what we've been through so far for some
of you will already be helpful. it would
have opened your eyes to something you'd
be like, "Ah, I know what I need to
start changing." But for most of you,
this will all be just a lot of talk so
far. Fluffy stuff, a lot of blah blah.
We often get people commenting on this
channel complaining that you're talking
too much. But the reason for that is
because if I just focus on the explicit
rule of the action that you need to
take, then if you're in a complex
situation or when you come across a
challenge or an obstacle that you're not
familiar with, you won't understand how
to adapt. and adapting is an important
part of trading. Whereas I believe if
you understand the logic behind things
and the rationale and you click with
that then you can take the right actions
in many different situations for the
rest of your career. So there is a lot
of talking behind this a lot of theory
or concepts behind the things that I
explain but the reason is because I want
you to deeply understand it. So just
stick with me but we are going to make
it a bit more practical and I'm going to
walk you through some examples now. So I
want to begin by giving you some simple
examples from other areas of the
industry. So other market participants
like investors and portfolio managers
and those will help you to understand
the concept. And then we'll go into what
it means for you as a retail trader,
spot trader and some of the main ways
that you make statements with your
trades. And then we'll wrap it up there.
And in the next video when we talk about
the next mental shift that's even more
critical than this one, this concept of
implicit statements will tie in closely
with that and we'll go into even more
detail then. So slowly you'll build your
understanding of this and it will be a
gamecher for you if you follow what
you're you're learning here. Okay. So
let me start with a really simple
example. Do you remember right at the
start of the COVID pandemic that we had
that situation where there were cruise
ships that had to be quarantined where
someone on board had corona virus. So
the entire cruise ship were not allowed
back on land and they had to be
quarantined for like a week or two and
there were a couple of them I think and
that was right at the start where you
know these headlines dominated every
media outlet. So everyone was paying
attention to the same news before
everything got so widespread that
everyone was paying attention to
different things. And so we ended up
with articles coming out like this one
over here saying, "Is this the end of
the line for cruise ships?" And as a
result of that, as you'd expect, some of
the major operators, their share prices
plummeted. Now for some poor investors
that would have invested here or
somewhere in this region around here
when things were relatively stable, some
of them would have still been holding
when the price got down here. Some of
them of course would have been lucky
enough to get out, hence why the price
was dropping as investors were trying to
get out of their positions, but some
people would still be holding here. And
some people that are holding here would
be choosing to stay holding. They'd
become bag holders, as we like to say.
Now, those people, if you ask them
what's their reason for holding, so you
met one of these people and they've got,
I don't know, £100,000 invested in Royal
Caribbean cruises, and you say to them,
"Why are you still holding?" They'd say
something like, "Well, eventually the
pandemic is going to end. People will go
back on like cruises. The whole company
will back to normal and the share price
will recover. So, rather than taking the
loss now, I'm going to hold on until
that happens." And you might listen to
them and say, "Yeah, it makes sense. I
could see that happening and it'll be
the same for other companies like I
remember at the start of the pandemic
cinema companies were suffering in a
similar way and so on and so on. So
that's the statement that they're making
that they are holding this because they
believe at some point the share price
will recover. But if you give it to
someone that's not going to be listening
to their statement but just going to
look at the actions they take, what is
the implicit statement they're making?
What are they implying by keeping their
money held up in this company or these
companies?
Well, they're implying that that's the
best place for their money. Because if
it wasn't the best place for their
money, they would sell their shares
right here and invested in something
else. And can we not all think of
companies that were destined to do so
much better than cruise companies during
the pandemic? For example, we all knew
that people are going to be working from
home, working remotely. People aren't
going to be out as much. Therefore,
video calls are going to be in demand.
So, companies like Zoom skyrock I was
going to say Zoom, but that's a bit too
cliche. Skyrocketed at that point. And
in fact, a company that was called Zoom
that wasn't even the video call Zoom
video conferencing company Zoom also
Zoomed. There you go. Done it. Because
people are too stupid to actually check
what company they're investing in.
They're like, "Take my money." And it
was a completely different company
called Zoom. Anyway, there are obviously
better places for the money during this
time. Even if you think it's going to
recover, there are always winners and
losers in any situation. If an industry
is collapsing, there are still winners
and losers. If an industry is taking
off, there are winners and losers.
Winners and losers in terms of companies
exist when there are paradigm shifts.
And when the pandemic started, that is a
major paradigm shift. So, of course,
these companies may recover somewhat,
but there are better places for your
money. If you took one of those
investors that were holding on, and if
somehow you could wipe their memory of
having these positions and say to them,
"Okay, I want you to look at the entire
market and pick out where you think the
most important industries are for you to
put your money or the best
opportunities. What do you think they
are?" Do you think any single one of
those people would choose cruise liners
that currently can't operate and people
aren't going on holidays? Of course not.
So the statement they're implying
doesn't align with what they actually
believe to be true. But cognitive
biases, you know, behavioral economics,
powerful thing. And people will convince
themselves that this position is
absolutely justified and it is the
biggest opportunity out there. And
they'll go through all kinds of
confirmation bias research looking at
previous case studies and convince all
their friends that they've got some
social proof and feel part of the crowd
and they'll hold on and think they're
doing the right thing. But it's not
necessarily the case.
And this relates to something that's
studied in behavioral finance called the
disposition effect. And you may have
heard of this before. It's a concept
from behavioral finance that describes
the tendency of investors to sell assets
that have increased in value while
keeping assets that have dropped in
value. So let's say for example that you
have a portfolio of companies, your
company A,
B, C,
D, and E.
Let's say company A since you bought the
company has gone up by 30%.
Company B has gone down by let's say
20%.
So that's down. C has gone up by 10%.
D has gone down by let's say 5%.
Just do a negative there as well. And E
has stayed the same. Okay. So you're
you're around break even where you
invested. So the disposition effect
shows that if you have an investor that
has these options and they need to uh I
mean options in alternative companies
not as in you know financial product
options. Um if you have them in this
situation and they need to liquidate for
some reason they need access to cash or
they are overexposed and you tell them
okay you need to um sell your shares in
two of these companies then what the
disposition effect shows is that people
have a tendency to exit the ones that
have made a profit and hold on to their
losing trades. There's a really
interesting book called the the art of
execution by I think it's Lee Freeman
Shaw who was a fund manager and he
invested money with he was basically a
fund of funds. We invested in different
funds and he used it as a way to study
what makes the best fund managers and
the worst fund managers, what makes good
investment and bad investment. And what
he found is that or you know what they
sort of what this the data was showing
them was that the companies that were
going up that that had risen since
they'd invested were the ones that
tended to continue rising, continue to
be a good investment. You know, a lot of
the time if this has dropped 20%,
there's a reason for that and companies
do continue into decline because there's
a drift to lower standards. Maybe it's
poor management that's led to them being
in that that situation in the first
place and so therefore it's likely to
continue. There's all kinds of reasons.
So people will take their profit simply
because similar to the cruise liners,
it's nothing to do with these being the
better investments. And it has
everything to do with loss aversion
which is a powerful
cognitive bias or let's say a quirk of
how our brains work that the impact of a
loss in terms of psychological weight is
of a higher value than uh a profit of
the same size. So it hurts us more to
make a loss of a certain amount than the
equivalent profit would make us feel
good. And when we have these situations,
it's all about the balance of
uncertainty.
Oops, weird writing. My writing is never
good, is it? Uncertainty versus
certainty.
So, in this situation where I'm up 30%,
if I decide to hold, then I have the
uncertainty of potentially making more
but potentially losing. Whereas, if I
close, I've got the certainty of having
a profit. So in this case, I'm going to
exit because I want the certainty of
having a profit. Whereas with B, where
I've lost 20%, if I continue to hold on,
I have the uncertainty of maybe making
the loss worse, but maybe getting out of
a loss or I have the certainty of taking
a loss. Well, the certainty means taking
a loss, so I won't take it. And so on
and so on. So people end up holding on
to their losers and closing their
profitable trades. But if you actually
took all these companies
at this point in time and they weren't
invested in them and you said to them
which are the companies that you'd most
like to put your money in, they probably
wouldn't choose the ones that were
losing because they'd look at them as
not being very good companies. There's
reasons that their share price is
falling. Maybe one of them has a good
opportunity because of that like it
represents value for money but you know
there's a a good chance they won't see
it that way. So disposition effect is
their brains way our minds work making
them take certain actions that don't
align with statements that they actually
believe to be true if they weren't
influenced by the money they have
invested. Now even though this
disposition effect and things like
holding on to those cruise companies
will still include professional
investors, fund managers, things like
that, it tends to be that the good
investors, professional investors, fund
managers understand how to express your
analysis in the right way that you're
making the right statements and not so
much getting influenced by other factors
that have no bearing on what the market
is showing you. So I want to talk you
through an example from back when I used
to manage a portfolio.
And what we used to do is well the the
main part of the portfolio is for
focusing on what we called special
opportunities. Now there is a category
of funds called special opportunities
funds that usually deal in things like
distressed assets. That's not what we
were doing. We just called it special
opportunities because it was for
situations where you had a big economic
event or a paradigm shift that could be
taking place and we wanted to make sure
we could capitalize on capitalize on it
in the most effective way. So what we do
is we'd identify what the situation was.
We'd understand which industries or
which asset classes or specific assets
are most likely to be affected by it.
And like I said before, in any situation
where there's a paradigm shift of some
sort, there will be winners and losers.
So we would want to identify where we
thought those hot spots were going to
be, where the winners and losers would
be. And in some situations, we didn't do
it so many times. So when I say some
situations, it's it sounds like it's a
lot of times, but it wasn't. um we would
put together a project team for it. So
for example when we were looking at the
fiscal cliff situation in the US around
what was it 201 I think end of 2012 2013
we put together a specialist group that
we hired just for that consultants who
were going to do research in different
areas because they had a specialism in
that area. So they weren't specialists
in terms of investing or analyzing
financial assets. They were specialists
from those areas so they could break
down an industry and understand what it
all means and where the hot spots are.
So for example, we did one looking at
the healthcare industry. So let's say
that we've done all of our research and
analysis. We've dissected the industry.
We've gone down the supply chain and we
figured out, hey, there's this company
here that if the big players start
suffering slightly and have to cut costs
and cut out contracts, this one way down
the line here is so reliant on this
situation that they're going to really
suffer. So what can we do next if we've
identified this is that company? Well,
most investors, most traders will think,
well, you could just short that company.
But there's a problem here because what
if the industry overall is going to
perform well? It's often the case that a
rising tide lifts all boats. And if the
industry is doing well, this company,
their share price could go up. So, I
might be right that they are going to
suffer in that particular area and their
share price could still rise and I could
end up losing money. So, what's the
alternative then? Well, you could do a
pairs trade where you choose a company
you think is going to do well then this
company and you go long the other
company short this one and it's the
difference between them. But the problem
with that is that you're also making
certain statements about the other
company and you're still exposed to
other things. For example, currency
fluctuations and other impacts on the
markets as a whole. It could be that
equities as an asset class are in demand
or not in demand. It could just be
inflows and outflows and things like
that due to the macroeconomic situation.
Whatever you're exposed to other things.
So the solution that we've come up with
is what we called a structured position.
Now structured positions and stuff often
refer to making an investment and having
an an option that's related to that that
you're capping your downside. It's
something that's used in banks quite
often for sort of wealth management
clients. It's not what I'm talking
about. We just came up with our own term
for this structured position. You can
think of it as just building a portfolio
around a particular opportunity. So we'd
identify, okay, what is it about this
company we want exposure to? We say,
okay, it's this thing here. This is what
we want exposure to. So we'd figure out
what we needed to offset to make sure
that this was the only thing that we are
going to be exposed to. So we'd hedge
off different exposures
by taking other positions. So that what
we are left with more or less and it
wouldn't be exact of course it wouldn't
but you know to a large extent that
we're left with this and so what you can
do then is take this position give it to
your alien who knows nothing about what
you're doing but understands the markets
and say okay look through these
positions and tell me what do you think
is the thing that I want exposure to and
by sort of cancelelling off all of these
things and saying okay this is all
offset they'd say oh you believe that
this is going to happen okay this
oversimplified version, but that's
essentially the idea of expressing your
analysis in an exact way through the
positions that you take. Now, this
approach of taking a structured position
only really works when you expect
there's going to be a big move in the
market. Otherwise, all of these other
positions that are offsetting something
about this are going to reduce and
reduce the return that you could
potentially make. Although, it would at
the same time be greatly reducing the
risk. So there is that benefit, but it's
only when you can expect there's going
to be something massively disruptive for
good or bad and therefore a big move in
the market that it made sense to do
this. But I just wanted to explain that
situation to you. So so you understand
this idea of making the right statements
that rather than just shorting the
company, you're making statements about
all kinds of things. It was structuring
a position. So you're making a statement
about the specific thing that you want
it to be. Now, this is something that I
think professional options traders,
people who are not just on Wall Street
Bets yoloing with some cool options or
something, taking the V trade, um that
it's something that option traders tend
to understand because the thing about
options is that you're not just having
to express whether you think an asset is
going up or down with different
strategies you could take with options,
different ways that you can put them
together. You can be expressing things
about time. You could be expressing
things about ranges of prices,
volatility, or combinations of different
things. And so, this is just a
screenshot from a book called I think
it's the the Bible of options trading. I
just wanted to put it here to show you
some of the different standard
strategies that are used and the
component parts and what the risk
profile ends up being. The idea is that
you can have your analysis about what
you think is going to happen and then
almost exactly express it in the
position that you open. So you ensure
that you're making the right statements
so that when the thing happens that you
think is going to happen, you are
profiting in the way that you expect.
And when things happen that you don't
think will happen or that you're you're
not wanting to happen, you're protected
against those. Like the statements
you're making through your actions are
exactly what you're intending them to
be. So you don't end up with unintended
consequences.
Now, I'm not saying that you need to go
and learn how to trade options. I very
rarely use options. I just want to show
you that around the industry there's
this understanding of expressing your
analysis with intended statements and
this is something that retail traders
don't tend to follow so much and like I
said earlier I think the reason for this
is that the trading industry almost
becomes like an echo chamber and all it
is is different people teaching things
that they've learned from someone else
who's learned it from someone else and
everyone talks about the same things
because they want to align with the
crowd because if you say something
different then everyone says no that's
not the right thing And essentially
these people don't have the experience
to understand the logic behind what
they're teaching. They're just spouting
out the same things. Not everyone, but a
lot of them. A big part of the industry.
So I want to show you examples of areas
of the same industry cuz we're all in
the same markets. Areas that are not
afraid of complexity that make things as
complex as they need to be or as simple
as they need to be, but as long as it's
making the right statements. And that's
the way I look at things as well. It's
not about complexity for the sake of
complexity. It's about complexity to
make sure that you're moving further
along the skill side of that continuum
and avoiding having un unintended
consequences and having things coming
down to luck. Okay. So, I know that that
was a lot of talking about things that
are not specific to probably the type of
trading that you're interested in, but
as I mentioned earlier, it's about
understanding the logic. And these
examples, I think, paint the picture in
a a much more easy to follow way than
just going straight to the trading part.
But I want to now switch our attention
to trading itself. And I'm going to show
my charts and and walk you through
things with an example of one of my
trades. But I want to start off with an
overall question that I want us to
answer because this is at the heart of
everything else. Now, if you've been
watching our videos here on this
channel, you would have heard me talk
about this time and time again, and I'm
going to keep talking about it time and
time again because slowly it's seeping
into other areas of this retail trading
industry. Um, but still people aren't
quite getting the logic correct. And if
you teach one part of it but not the
actual correct logic, then it's just
going to end up being useless. So, we're
going to keep coming back to this. So,
what I want you to do is imagine that
you were following this chart. So, it's
not from this point, but just as time
was going on, you were following this
chart and you were going to set an alarm
that was going to go off at random
times. So, it might go off now and then
again in 15 minutes. Another time it
might be in 5 hours, 22 minutes, you
know, random times. And whenever that
alarm goes off, you're going to flip a
coin, heads or tails to go long or
short. So heads will be long, tails will
be short. So you have no advantage in
terms of timing the market and you have
no advantage in terms of direction that
you're trading. So it's all completely
random. Okay? So you might have ended up
with um it going off here, here, here,
here, here, here, anywhere, right? and
then it's completely random whether it's
long or short. So if that's the case at
any point in time if the alarm's gone
off, you can't see the chart and I flip
the coin long or short and we're going
to do it as a one to one riskreward.
What do you think is the likelihood of
you ending up with a profit from that
trade? Would you expect that you're
definitely going to lose cuz it's
random? Because if that's the case, then
you could just take the opposite side of
that. No, we'd say if it's a 1:1
riskreward, you have a 50% chance of
profit, 50% chance of loss. Okay. What
if you do exactly the same thing? Flip
the coin. This time it's going to be a
one to two riskreward.
So, you're still choosing heads or tails
based on flipping the coin. You have no
advantage for the timing. What's the
probability of a profit?
Well, in this case, it's going to be 33
and a3%.
If it's a 1 to three, what's it going to
be? It's going to be a 25% chance of
profit. 1 to 4 is going to be 20%. And
so on and so on. Now, at Duomo, we call
all of these
these percentages
the base rate probability.
And it's basically the probability if
you had no advantage in the market. And
the way you can think about this is to
go through a calculation that we call
the trade expectancy calculation.
Having to do a lot of writing here and
my writing is terrible.
So trade expectancy. Simple way to do
this is you take what would be the
profitable outcome. So let's say
profit outcome
multiplied by the probability of that
minus
loss outcome
multiply by the probability of that
and this will equal your trade
expectancy. So for these ones that we've
just gone through, the reason that these
are the base rate probabilities is
because when you put them in this
calculation, let's do the first one.
Oops, didn't mean to do that little line
there. Let's undo that. Let's do the
first one. What was the profitable
outcome? It was 1 times by the
probability was 50%. So that's 0.5
minus loss outcome 1 multiplied by 0.5.
It's going to equal zero. So all of
those base rate probabilities, it's
because when you put them through this
calculation, you end up with zero. So
here's the thing. When you open that
trade, that's a one one, you might end
up with a profit, you might end up with
a loss. And that doesn't mean that it
was a 100% chance of a profit or 100%
chance for loss. It was still 50%. It
just ended up being the profit or loss
in that occasion. But if you open those
trades, any of these riskreward ratios
with no advantage again and again,
you're going to end up with something
like this. So you may have seen in
studies on something called the law of
large numbers
that you'll have coin toss trials often
used as the example to show you that
concept, the law of large numbers. And
so what you'll see here is that this is
50%, this is 0%, this is 100%. And this
is number of times that it lands on
heads. And along this way is how many
coin flips. So if we're flipping that
coin and it lands on heads, oh look,
right, let me do a different color.
Look, we're all the way up here, 100%.
Next one lands on heads, still 100%.
Next one lands on heads, 100%. Next one
lands on tails, it's going to drop a
bit. And maybe we have a few tails in a
row. So it drops down here. Then we get
some heads and and so on. And eventually
over time it's going to drift towards
the expected value which will be 50% if
it's an equally weighted coin. This is
after maybe like a,000 coin flips down
here. So here might be like after 10
after 100
and so on. Okay. If you look online for
the law of large numbers examples,
you'll always see this coin flip trial
thing. And it's the same with these
trades where you have no advantage where
the expectancy is zero. You can expect
this except for one critical factor. And
obviously in the case the expectancy
that wouldn't be 50% there. This would
not be 50%, it would be uh 0%. Right?
Except for one critical factor that
every time you open a trade
you're paying a transaction cost.
My writing is getting lazier and lazier.
Things like the spread,
commissions,
uh, swaps, whatever it might be. So,
every trade costs you, whether it's a
profit or a loss. So, if over the long
run you're going to end up at 0%, then
actually, and that's from the trades
itself, actually the accumulation of
transaction costs going to put you in a
loss.
This is why most traders end up losing
when they have no advantage. You know,
there's this joke that people say a lot
of the time when a trader is losing, oh,
you should just take the opposite side
of the trade. But it's not the case.
It's usually that they're not picking up
on anything of any note in the markets.
It's the equivalent of what I've just
shown you. But they don't realize that.
And the thing that puts them into a loss
over time is just the accumulation of
transaction costs. And they think, oh,
it's because I've been losing more
trades and if I took the opposite side,
I would have been profitable. it's just
not the case. You still would have end
up losing because you're taking the
opposite side of something that has an
expected value of zero, but you're
paying a transaction cost that is going
to be there all the time. Okay? So, I
want you to keep all this in mind. Now,
I know that I've explained all of this
on this channel before, but I want to
keep reiterating it so that people start
to understand this more and more. But
what I want you to think about is this.
Let's say you're blindfolded. You can't
see the charts. I pick a random moment.
I flip a coin and it's heads or tails,
long or short, and I say we're going to
enter a trade and it's going to be one
to three risk return. So, it's going to
be a loss of 30 pips against a profit of
90 pips. And I say, do you want to take
the trade? Now, most sane, rational
people will say no because there's no
advantage and it would take a real
gambler to say yes.
But in some situations, traders are
taking a 1 to three risk return trade.
Why? What is the statement that they're
making in that case? Now, some traders
think that the statement they're making
is that I think this is going to end up
being profitable. As in they're trying
to predict the future like a fortune
teller or something like some Mystic
Meg. I had to bring it up because I
always mention Mystic Meg. Okay, anyone
that's watching this channel for the
first time is going to be like, "What
the hell is he going on about?" But I
don't know what the reason is, but
Mystic Meg just seems to come up in my
content more often than she should.
She's like living in my mind rent free
it seems. Anyway, people think that
that's what they're doing. I'm entering
this trade because I think it's going to
be profitable.
But we all know that nothing is certain
in the markets. You know, all it would
take is you enter a long trade. Even if
you think it's 100% chance of ending up
in profit, a big whale comes in the
market, unloads a position, price drops,
and you end up with a loss. You know,
can you predict that they are not going
to do that? Of course not. It could
happen. You could have a war that
starts, natural disaster, anything could
happen that could disrupt the markets.
So it's always a probability. So we are
making a statement about probabilities.
So what is that statement that we're
making? So let's say we have that 3:1
trade. We know that the base rate is
going to be a 75% chance of the loss,
25% chance of the profit. So that would
have an expected value of zero. So if
we're taking this trade, we are surely
making the statement that the
probability of a profit is higher than
this and therefore the probability of a
loss is lower than this. Okay? So we're
not making a statement that the profit
is more likely. You might think you're
making that statement, but opening a
trade, we're not necessarily making that
statement that the profit is more likely
because it would take a lot of an edge
to shift these probabilities that this
is more likely than this. It's just
there's such a huge gap there. But
really, all you need is an advantage
here. So for this to be a little bit
higher than this and you're going to
have positive expectancy for that trade,
which means if you take a trade over and
over and over and over again over a
large sample size, you're going to be
profitable overall as long as the
difference is big enough to overshadow
the cost that you're paying, the
transaction cost. Now, don't worry if
you're not following. We'll discuss this
in the coming videos as well, but I just
want to point out like, okay, that's the
statement we're making. The more we can
connect with that statement rather than
thinking we're having to predict the
outcome, the exact outcome that's going
to happen, but instead think we just
need to find where there's an advantage,
then this completely changes everything.
And you're going to see from the next
statements that we talk through how it
relates to this. And the more you can
start shifting your thinking to this,
the better your trading will be, the
more you'll set yourself up for success.
Okay? So, this is the statement that
we're making. And listen, when we think
about things in this way, it could be
that we actually think that there's only
a small advantage over base rate. So
this rather than being 25% is 27%. Or we
could think there's a really big
advantage like rather than this being
25% it's actually 60% or something crazy
like that. And that will be expressed in
a different part of your trade which
I'll point out to you. But the simple
fact that we're opening the trade is
expressing this as a statement that we
think there's an advantage over the base
rate regardless of what that advantage
is. So I want to bring in the charts and
talk you through some of the other
statements that we're making. So give me
a second. Okay. So I want to walk you
through some of the key statements that
we're making from a highle point of
view. As I mentioned earlier in the
video, this it's not like a series, but
the next couple of videos are going to
follow along this theme of mental shifts
that you need to make to change your
perception of trading that will set you
up for success. And in particular, the
very next one really closely relates to
this idea of making statements in the
markets because that's a big part of it.
In fact, the making statements is a big
part of all of them, but specifically
that next one. So, we'll go into detail
with other aspects of this in that video
and help solidify your understanding of
this overall concept. But for now, it's
just about giving you some highle ones
that you click with it and you go,
"Okay, I get it now." Now, to help you
understand these statements, I'm
actually going to walk you through them
by showing you an example of one of my
trades from this week. And it's not that
I've cherrypicked the most spectacular
trade. It was just a pretty standard
short-term trade. It just happens to be
the last trade that I took. It was this
week. And obviously this YouTube, this
trading view replay mode, so anyone can
say anything about what trades they have
or haven't taken. But I actually do live
stream trading sessions a few times a
week in our community. And this was a
trade that on Monday morning, I'd
already walked our members through it
and explained exactly the setup that I
was waiting for and that I said then
that I would be taking that trade and
some of our members took it as well. So
when the entry came at 5:00 p.m. that
day, it was what I'd already outlined
that morning. So take from that what you
will. Now, obviously, as you can see,
there's no analysis on this because
that's not the topic of this video, and
I don't want to distract from the things
we're talking about because people get
caught up on, "Oh, I would have done it
this way. I wouldn't have done that. You
should have done this." It's just noise
that ends up happening. So, instead, if
you do want to have a breakdown of this
trade or my trades in general, see the
analysis, understand the rationale,
click the link in the description box to
sign up for our newsletter where you'll
get more trading and stuff. but also
like I mentioned earlier the the weekend
Nicholas's notes emails where there's
some trading insights and then also a
breakdown of some of my trades. So then
you can see it exactly what was behind
this one. All right. So what statements
are we making? Well, the very first
statement we make actually comes way
before we do any meaningful analysis or
find an opportunity or anything like
that. And it's an area that I think most
traders actually neglect and don't give
enough thought and attention. And it's
about your choice of market. You know,
imagine you take whatever markets,
whatever asset it is that you're
following in the trading session, or
maybe it's several markets, and you go
and give it to that alien cuz we're
keeping them busy and you say, "Why am I
following these markets?" Well, they
that alien or anyone really would assume
that if you're choosing to spend your
time focused on those markets, then it
must surely be because you have some
sort of advantage or because you have a
reason to believe that that particular
market is going to be more likely to
give you opportunities than other
markets for a particular reason. So,
having an advantage might mean that you
have some specialist knowledge in a
particular market. Maybe you um you're
looking at a particular equity or a
commodity and you've worked in a
relevant industry. Or maybe you're
trading a certain currency pair because
you were on that currency desk at a bank
for decades. You know, whatever it might
be, you have something that other people
don't have. Or with the opportunities,
it might be because you've spotted
something about that particular market
that leads to the type of opportunities
that you're looking for. Because it's
just like when we were talking about the
cruise liners earlier that when they
were invested in those cruise companies,
they were making the implicit statement
that this is the best place for my
money. Otherwise, they could have sold
their shares and put their money
elsewhere. In a very similar way, when
we're following a market for a trading
session, we are making the implicit
statement that this is the best place to
spend my time because if not, you would
be following a different market. So
there are advantages of following one
market through thick and thin because
you develop a certain implicit knowledge
that you wouldn't have otherwise. A
connection with the market, a deeper
understanding. But there will be periods
with any asset, any market where there
are periods of really shitty activity
where you know that it's not going to be
great opportunities and either you end
up forcing things that you know you
shouldn't be trading or you don't trade
during that period or you just burn your
mental energy trying to figure things
out before you find like a trade that's
like barely anything. And so in those
moments you could be switching to other
markets that are better and you wouldn't
lose the implicit knowledge that you've
gained. So people just stick with one
market cuz they think that's the right
thing to do or they don't want to focus
on other markets. Or some people will
say, well, it's because my strategy
works with that market. And that's
usually a good sign for and this is
going to get me in trouble with some
people, but it's usually a good sign
that actually your trading approach
doesn't work and you're riding a wave of
luck. You know, if you get a bunch of
data from a random trading approach,
then it's the law of small numbers.
you'll be able to find one market out of
the bunch of markets you've looked at
that outperform the others because
that's what happens when you've got
small sample sizes and then people stick
with it and say, "Oh, it works only on
this market." On the other hand, you
have traders who skim through lots of
different markets during a session and
just wait until they see a setup or
something on one of them and they go and
trade that and then they lose out on any
kind of implicit knowledge from
different markets. They burn mental
energy throughout the entire session
doing endless amounts of analysis. So
when it actually comes to the point of
opening the trade and managing the trade
when their decision- making matters the
most, they don't have the energy to do
it as effectively as they could have
done if they had saved their mental
energy and they become too reactive.
They see something coming up, they jump
into it, they force things, it just
doesn't lead to good trading. So after
many years of doing this and having seen
it with many other traders, I firmly
believe that great trades come from
great market selection. So, I always
encourage everyone to have a market
selection process. And actually, just
like with the other things I was saying
about making statements, this is
something that you tend to see investors
doing a lot more than traders because
there aren't many investors out there
who are going to sit and read through
the financial reports of every single
company in the S&P or something like
Warren Buffett does. Instead, they're
going to use something like a stock
screener where they put in certain
criteria that are aligned with the type
of opportunities they're looking for and
it will filter out the most of the
companies so that they're left with a
short list to go and research. So,
that's a form of market selection. It's
making sure that their time and their
mental energy is spent where it's more
likely to lead to opportunities that
they actually want to pursue. And
traders don't tend to think this way.
But I will be putting out a video very
soon that's all about the market
selection process after the next couple
that I've got planned that are about
these mental shifts because I think
everyone needs a market selection
process. And just briefly with this one.
So I chose this market for this
particular session. It was Monday, what
was that the 1st of September I think
because it met certain criteria for
certain type of opportunity that I look
for. And so the thing that I do, you can
see over here is that I have this
section up here for my session focus.
and I'll have sometimes one, sometimes
two, maybe three, like just a few
markets that I'm focusing on for the
session. Then I've got backup markets
that are in a decent area for looking
for opportunities, but not the ones I
want to focus on. So, if one of these
markets, like the thing that I'm focused
on them for, disappears, like some
something disrupts that market, and now
it's not looking like a good area for
the opportunity, I'll take it out of
there, add one of these in there
instead. And then there are others that
I'm not following, but maybe I've
updated analysis and I'll maybe move
them into backup markets when when I
need to. And then I have these colored
tags and these represent the different
types of opportunities that I am looking
for because I don't just want to follow
the markets until a trade comes up. If a
trade does come up that's positive
expectancy, I'll take it. But I'd rather
my attention is focused on specific
types of opportunities that I know will
give me the best bang for my buck. The
way I think about it is this. We can
think about uh time. So holding periods
and potential returns and you have high
low and you have low
high. You can think of it as like
quadrants.
So obviously the the best situation is
low amount of time, high return. Then
you've got high amounts of time, high
return, which is okay. And what you
definitely don't want is low return,
high time. So you don't want these ones.
So, the preference is I want to find
situations like this. If I can't find
those, I want ones that are like this.
And if I can't find those, I'll go for
ones that are like this. And I never
want these ones.
Okay? We'll discuss all of this another
another time. But it's it's part of
having a good weekly or daily routine to
find these things. But anyway, when we
are following a market, that's the
statement we're making. This is the best
use of my time. So have a think about
your trading and think if you genuinely
think that with the market you're
following each day or if you're forcing
things because I always think in the
markets you can't polish a turd.
Sometimes markets are just during
that period of time and rather than
forcing yourself to find something there
just move to an easier market. Make life
easy for yourself. Okay. So we've chosen
the market. We've gone through our
analysis which by the way as you might
have guessed we're also making certain
statements but that's all what we'll
discuss in the next video. and we get to
the point where we think there could be
an opportunity. Now, there are a couple
of statements that we're making here.
And by the way, I just noticed that
Euroad is highlighted here because
that's the last one I chose from this
list. But we are looking at Aussie CAD.
Just want to make that clear in case
anyone starts looking for this point on
this chart. It's cuz I had to just open
a different broker one for Aussie so
that I'm not disrupting my own analysis
when I remove everything from the chart.
Okay. So, what's the first statement
that we're making? Well, it's going to
be about timing. What's the reason that
we're opening the trade right now and
not before, not after? Why now? Is there
a reason to think that now is the right
time? Now, some people don't have a
reason with timing because they don't
know with the short-term movements
whether it's going one way or another or
what the chances are of that or where
there's the better area of opportunity.
They just know about the bigger picture
opportunity. So then they're sort of
aligning with the famous statement from
reminiscences of a stock operator where
uh the guy who is basically Jesse
Livermore is told by the older
experienced guy that sometimes you just
need to be in the market. If you believe
that it's going up, be in the market.
Don't try and time it. So some people
think that. But for those of you that do
try and time the market, what's the
statement you're making? You're saying
that now is the right time. And if we
think about what we went through before
about when we're entering a trade, what
is the statement we're making there?
about expectancy. Well, if we are
entering a trade now and not before or
after, the statement could be that this
is optimal
for expectancy.
Or alternatively, it could be that right
now you see that you've got positive
expectancy, but there's a chance that if
you wait, it won't have positive
expectancy. So, you'd rather take the
trade now, even if it could be better
expectancy, because it could also be
worse and then there not be an
opportunity. Okay, I know it's a bit of
a mouthful to explain. So, positive
expectancy
that may go away.
Now, what we don't want to be making
statements about is the situation I see
happening a lot for traders where there
could be an opportunity.
And the key word here is could as in
it's not currently an opportunity, but
there may be a setup coming. and they're
so worried about missing it, they get
anxious that they enter the trade and
it's because of FOMO. So, if you take
away the FOMO bit that someone else
can't feel for you, you feel the FOMO,
but they can't feel it. So, if they give
you an objective view of your trade that
you've taken, then they'll be saying,
"Okay, right now you think it's positive
expectancy." And if actually you don't
think that, then there shouldn't have
been a reason for you taking that trade.
So in the case of this trade, my timing
was after the close of this candle.
There was a particular setup. There was
a reason for entering right then based
on analysis from multiple time frames.
So at the close of this candle, it was
5:00 p.m. UK time. Entered short. Now
the fact that I'm entering as we
discussed before is that I'm expressing
a statement about the expectancy
of the opportunity. I'm saying that the
probabilities
higher probabilities than base rate.
Okay. Now, obviously, if I'm going to
make that statement, then I need to
understand what the probabilities are.
But I can't estimate the probabilities
of something without first knowing what
that something is. And this is something
that I think a lot of traders actually
get quite wrong. For example, there are
lots of traders that trade based on
purely indicator-based strategies and
ones where they'll enter when the
indicator shows them something and then
exit when the indicator changes to show
them something else. So, let me show you
what I mean with a quick example of one
that I think most traders learn when
they first start when they're
experimenting with different strategies
until they quickly realize it's useless.
A moving average crossover strategy. So,
you maybe have moving average like this.
It's not going to be visually accurate,
but I'm just doing this to to paint the
picture. So, let's say that you have
these two levels and it crosses over
here and it's an indication that you're
going to go short. It wouldn't make
sense with the structure we have here,
but anyway. So,
you are going to go short here. Okay,
maybe it's here that it happens.
Now, if we're going short, then we're
saying that we think the probabilities
are better than the base rate. But how
can you say that when you don't know
where you'll be exiting the trade? Do we
know ahead of time where these will
cross back over again to exit the trade?
No. So then how do we know what the
potential outcomes are? And if we don't
know what the potential outcomes are,
how can we estimate the probabilities of
something? Know how if I say price could
go up and it could go down, estimate the
probabilities of that. Well, the first
thing you're going to know is well, how
far up or down? And that's exactly the
problem here. So, we can't call this an
opportunity if we don't know where we're
going to be exiting because how do we
know that we've got an advantage over
the base rate? And that's exactly what
lots of traders do when they do things
like this where they'll say, "Okay,
price has been doing this and now it
started to break out. So, I'm going to
go long because I think it's more likely
to go up." Well,
go up where? And more likely than what?
I mean, one pip, 10 pips, 30 pips, and
then maybe they'll put their stop loss
down here. They say it's more likely to
go up than to hit that stop loss. Well,
sure. But if you're talking about it
going this far and the stop losses here,
then that's asymmetric against you. So,
it's like, you know, it might be that's
a one to four or something. In which
case, you're expecting that there's an
80% chance of it hitting your profit
rather than hitting your loss. But if
you don't have an advantage over your
base rate, then the expectancy is still
going to be zero. So yes, it's more
likely to hit that profit target, but
you're not going to make money doing
that over the long run. You're going to
lose. So we need to define where we're
exiting. And a lot of trades will say,
"Oh, I exit when it shows signs of, you
know, that is reversing." Well, fine,
but you need to know ahead of time at
least a minimum of it. Now, this ties in
very closely to what we'll be talking
about in the next session. So, I don't
want to get too deep into this because
I'll really outline a lot of the
different statements that people are
making without realizing it there. But,
if we just accept for now that we need
to understand the potential outcomes and
the probabilities and if we're wanting
to estimate the probability of something
and to be accurate, then it can't just
be an an outcome that we've chosen sort
of arbitrarily. It has to be based on
something because it needs to be
something that can be measured and
tracked in some way based on something
that has meaning. And again, that's
something we'll elaborate on in the next
session. So, we have the fact that we're
following this market in the first
place, that this is a better place for
us to spend our time rather than a
different market. We have the fact that
we think something is an opportunity, is
a statement about probabilities being
better than the base rate, which implies
then we understand about what the
potential outcomes are in order to be
able to say that the probabilities are
better, that we have some advantage. We
have the timing entering short at the
close of this candle. And then finally,
we have the position size. So the
position size, how much you're going to
be risking on a trade. We are making a
statement with that. So let's think
about the statements we're making here.
So some traders use what we call static
position sizes or static percentages at
risk. So that means that for every
single trade, the percentage at risk is
the same. So let's say for every trade
they risk 1%. Oh, that was a really
weird percentage sign. There we go. Or
some people use static position sizes,
which means that the position size for
every trade is the same like maybe it's
one loss or something. And so what
statements are being made here? Well, if
it's the same percentage of risk,
they're saying that every opportunity is
equal to them. There's no
differentiation. They don't want to be
risking more on a better opportunity,
risking less on a worse opportunity. All
of them are the same. And if you're
using a static position size where it's
like one lot per trade, but you're using
different exit points in a loss, so
different placements for a stop-loss or
something, then that means that in some
situations you're risking more and in
some situations you're risking less, but
it's not defined by the opportunity
itself. It's defined by how far the stop
loss is. So let's say you have
opportunity A and opportunity B. And in
opportunity A, the stop loss is 20 pips.
and opportunity B, the stop loss is 50
pips,
then if you're using a static position
size, so one lot for every trade, you're
risking more for this trade than this
trade. So therefore, if you give it to
the alien who's going to have an
objective view of it, they'll say you
think this is the better opportunity.
That's why you're risking more of your
capital on it. But it might be the case
that you think this one is. So where's
the logic there? the statement you're
making doesn't align with what you
actually think. And some people aren't
even thinking about which opportunity is
better or worse. So they they don't know
whether they're making the right
statement or not. So instead, it's much
better if we use a dynamic position size
where the amount that we're risking is
aligned with what we think of the
opportunity. So for example, for some
trades you might risk 0.5, another one
you might risk 0.6, another you might be
risking 0.8, another 1.5, and so on and
so on. But the key question then is how
do you choose the percentage at risk?
Well, we can think through what
statement is the percentage at risk
making? Well, it's going to be making a
statement about the quality of the
opportunity.
And how do we know the quality of an
opportunity? What's the best measure of
how good an opportunity is? It's going
to come down to expectancy.
If you run the expectancy calculation
and you find that one trade is going to
give you an average of 0.5R
for each trade that you open, which
means whether it ends up being a profit
or a loss, if you keep taking that trade
over and over a thousand times, then on
average it would have generated 0.5 R
per trade. So if you've got that one and
then you've got another one that's
actually uh 0.8 R, well, which one is
the better opportunity?
this one. It might be that this one over
here is more likely to result in a
profit for that specific trade based on
the probabilities, but this one is the
better opportunity. So, which one's
better to have the higher amount at
risk? This one here.
Now, there is an aspect of trading
psychology here, and I've talked about
this in a video before. I'll put it on
screen actually so you can click up
there to watch it if you want where some
trades will have a much better
expectancy but a higher probability of
losing and therefore you can expect a
draw down to occur in the short term and
if you're risking more on those trades
the draw down's going to be deeper and
for some people this is going to trigger
things like the break even effect or not
being able to make the same decision-m
that they should be making where they
will start taking actions and decisions
that are making the wrong statements
because they are going through some sort
of loss aversion or revenge trading and
things like that, but that's out of the
scope of this video. You can click that
video up there and and learn about that.
Okay, so all of that is at the the entry
point of the trade. Okay, so there's all
these statements that are being made.
We've got the fact that you're entering
a trade is making a statement about
having an advantage. The position size
or percentage at risk is making a
statement about how much of an advantage
you have. Okay. So, what this means is
that you could take that trade, give it
to someone else, and ask them what
statements I'm making, and they'll be
able to tell, okay, the fact you're
entering a trade means you think there's
an advantage over base rate. The fact
you risked more on this trade than this
one means that you think the advantage
is bigger on this trade than this one.
Okay. So in the case of this trade, my
trade, you obviously know that this was
the entry point and the timing of that
was based on that being the specific
point where I expected there to be a
shift in activity, which means whatever
activity was causing the imbalance that
caused the move up to that point. There
was likely to be a shift in activity
there that would either put an end to
that imbalance and potentially cause an
imbalance the other way. Okay, there's
something I identified there that I
thought would cause that shift in
activity. So that's a defined point. I
can then look at where the next shift in
activity could be. So the next outcome
this way, negative outcome. And I could
do the same for this way. So let's say
it was down to here and up to here. Then
in terms of my stop loss or where I
would exit in a loss if it was moving
against me, then I would place that stop
loss at the point beyond which the
probabilities of the negative outcome
playing out are so much higher than the
possibility of the positive outcome
playing out that the expectancy beyond
that point is negative. So I call it the
tipping point of the trade. Tipping
point where things have shifted. Okay.
So that's where the stop loss goes. And
then in terms of the positive move, so
profitable move, I don't use a takerit
level. I use what I call a TMP. It's a
trade move potential. Another way to
think about this is just the first
decision point. And there's a good
reason for this and it kind of ties into
the next bit which is all about what you
do during the trade. So I see many
traders opening trades with these huge
asymmetric risk return ratios. Like I've
heard this crazy statement where and
it's from a really popular YouTube
channel and company that teaches people
how to trade the nonsense approach um
where they say when this chart pattern
happens then in 90% of the cases it's
going to reverse the entire impulse move
that led to it. and they end up with
something like this where it's like okay
pattern here breaks that and they're
putting their stop loss here and then
their take profit down here and they end
up with a trade that's like a 10 to one
or something 1 to 10. So let's say for
example that is a 1 to nine just cuz it
keeps the maths easier. So if you got a
1 to n risk return
then the base rates let's do br those
are going to be 90% chance of a loss and
10% chance of the profit. So for us to
say it's the other way around you have
to have such a massive edge and if you
just do the expectancy calculation of
this being the other way around where
rather than it being a 90% chance of
loss it's actually 10% chance of loss
and 90% chance of the profit. Okay. And
figure out the expectancy of that and
imagine you're taking those trades every
day and just see what a short amount of
time it would take for you to be like
basically the richest man in the world.
I mean, it's it's completely ridiculous
and it shows a real lack of
understanding of probabilities and how
the markets work. But anyway, that's a
topic for another time. The point I want
to make for now is about what statements
you're making if you have these huge
riskreward ratios. So, let me make it
really clear for you. So, let's say that
you've got that move up that's happened
and you decide, okay, this is going to
be where my stop loss is and my takerit
is going to be down here and I'm going
to use a set and forget approach. Okay,
set and forget.
Okay, so what statement are we making?
If we have a set and forget trade,
that's a one to nine riskreward.
We are saying that there's nothing that
can happen between this point here and
this point here that will disrupt this
trade in any way or lead me to exiting
sooner. That is the point down here.
That's the only point I want to exit.
But here's the thing. The traders who
take those trades, if you say to them,
first of all, okay, I get that you think
it's going to retrace all of this
impulse move. How long will it take to
do that? Well, they can lie and give you
a time. Oh, it usually happens 90% of
the time in 2 days or some But
if they're being honest, they'll say, "I
don't know." Because no one knows. It
could take weeks. It could take months.
It could take hours. Who knows? It might
do it like this. It might do it like
this. It might never do it. Right? We
don't know. So, okay, if we don't know
how long it will take. Could it be that
it takes a week? Yes. Could it be it
takes two weeks? Yes. Okay. During that
time, could something happen that
disrupts the trade that's out of your
control? Could there be a natural
disaster? Could there be a war? Could
there be a central bank decision? Could
there be something to do with tariffs?
Could there be NFP? Could there be
earnings releases? Is there something
that could disrupt it? Oh yes, NFP might
come out in between and that could
disrupt it. Okay, so there's something
that could happen that could disrupt the
trade. Now are there any levels in
between where if the price struggled
there you would think oh this is not
looking so good and that somehow
whatever you thought at this point in
time time the probabilities have
changed. Usually they'll say yes like
for example if price
gets to here and struggles and then it's
back here they'll probably say okay it's
not really going to work out. Okay, so
there are things between this point here
and this point here that could disrupt
the trade, right? So if those things
happen, they have two choices then. They
can either exit the trade early or they
can hold on to the trade stubbornly just
because they set it as a set and forget
knowing that the trade has been
disrupted. And in both cases, the
original plan they had for the trade or
the original statements they were making
don't make sense. Because remember when
we enter that trade we are making a
statement
about probabilities. Okay. So this is
base rate. We're making a statement
about these. We're saying that the
probability of this is higher than this
and the probability of this is lower
than this. Okay. Now if you're exiting
sooner
well it's not a 1 to nine anymore. Maybe
it's a 1 to four. So then the
probabilities are different. Do you
still have an advantage? How do you
know? And if you're holding on to that
trade and something has happened at this
point that's disrupted it, well then the
probabilities are different to what you
were anticipating at this point in time.
So still the calculation is different.
Now I'm not saying that it can't be that
you still have an edge for that move
there. What I'm saying is that you could
be opening yourself up to unintended
consequences because you were not
factoring that in at the point of entry
and therefore the expectancy
calculation, the whole rationale for the
trade is different. So you've made an
inaccurate statement. You've made an
implicit statement through your actions
that you didn't follow up with, that you
didn't believe in. So that's why I use
TMP because I'm not setting a
take-profit level there and exiting
because I'm not saying that's
necessarily the extent of the trade. I'm
just saying that's the first point where
I'd want to make a decision. But that
decision is exiting the trade, moving
stop-loss, scaling out, whatever. Now,
there are two big advantages of doing
things this way of using the TMP, the
first decision point in the way that I'm
explaining. And they're all about making
the right statements. Surprise,
surprise. So the first thing is that if
I use the TMP, the first decision point
in my expectancy calculation to assess
whether it's an opportunity that's worth
taking, I'm basing that calculation on
worst case scenario rather than what
many traders do, which is best case
scenario. So having a riskreward ratio
of a 1:9 or 1:10 knowing that you'd
probably exit sooner is making your
calculations about whe this an
opportunity based on best case
scenarios.
I'm using worst case scenarios. Why?
Because I want to make sure that my
statements are accurate. So, if I'm
saying that there's a chance things
could be disrupted in the markets or I
don't know what the markets will be like
when it gets here, but I know that
regardless, I won't make a decision
until it's there. So, I won't exit any
sooner than this cuz that's the first
order outcome. Then my statement is
going to be accurate. Okay? So, the
probability of it getting here has to
count the fact that it could get
disrupted on route and head this way.
But that means that I'm using the worst
case scenario. Okay? Rather than
assuming the best. The second thing is
that my probabilities
are going to be more accurate because
the further ahead you go, the further
out from the current price, the further
ahead in time, the more inaccurate your
probability estimates are going to be
because you don't know what will be
happening at that point in time.
If this is just here, I can assume what
the price will be like approaching that
point. Can I assume what the price will
be like all the way over here or like a
week later? No. It could be moving with
momentum. Activity could have completely
dried up to nothing. It could be
reacting to every level there. It could
be that something's happened in the
market. It's completely transformed
everything. Anything could happen. So,
how can I rely on a probability estimate
way out there in the future? You can't.
So, maybe the person taking this trade
had an advantage right at the point of
entry, but beyond a certain point is
going from skill into luck because they
have no idea what the price will be like
down here. And so either they're going
to exit early or they're holding on
based on luck. And that's what I don't
want to be doing. So I use TMP
and then I make my decision. And in this
case, I won't talk you through the whole
uh what my strategy for this opportunity
was. And when I talk about strategy, I'm
not talking about the way most people
talk about strategy is like a predefined
thing they're doing. I'm talking like
the strategy for this specific
opportunity.
Again, I've said a million times that's
something we will be discussing in a
separate video soon. Okay. So let's
really quickly talk about what then
happens during the trade. So what
statements are being made here? So this
is what happened next. We then reach TMP
where I've got to make a decision. So we
talk about trade management, the actions
you take when you're in a trade. But at
Duomo, we also call that same thing
strategic risk management. And the
reason we call it strategic risk
management is because if you think about
it, once you're in a trade, all of the
actions that you can take are some form
of risk management. Whether you realize
that or not, you could scale out. So,
taking part of your profit, that means
reducing risk.
You could scale in, which means
increasing risk.
You can move your stop-loss.
So, of course, you can widen the stop
loss, which means you're increasing your
risk, or you can tighten the stop loss,
which means reducing risk. And then you
can exit the trade where you're removing
your exposure completely. no exposure.
So you're managing your risk in a
strategic way. It's strategic risk
management. So really there's a limited
number of things we could do when the
trades open that fall under strategic
risk management or trade management. And
obviously there are other things that we
can use like derivatives or you know but
that's not really what we're focused on
here. So we have to think about what
statement we're making with those. And
the funny thing is all of the trade
management stuff is just the same stuff
we're doing at the points of entry but
just on an existing position. So if you
think at the points of entry we're
looking at possible negative outcome,
possible positive outcome and the
probabilities of them. And at the time
of entering we have a stop loss which is
the what I call the tipping point. The
point beyond which the probability of
this is so far that it ends up being
negative expectancy. We have the
percentage at risk is going to be based
on the expectancy. But what happens when
you're already in a trade? So at this
point, well, my stop loss would still be
where it was originally. Does it need to
be there? Am I not wanting to cap the
point beyond which it's negative
expectancy? So I could move my stop
loss. If then based on the next
potential outcomes, because obviously
this is one outcome, I could look at the
next outcomes. The expectancy is worse
than at the points of entry. I can look
at the percentage I have at risk and
reduce that. If at some point the
expectancy improves, I can increase the
percentage of risk. So, it's just the
same as what you're doing at the point
of entry, but on an active position. So,
in my case, as I'm at that first
decision point, I have a trade that's
broken across two different time
horizons. And for the short time
horizon, the expectancy has now changed.
So, I chose to exit 30% of the position.
And then later on, we have another move
down and we end up in this region. And I
exit another 30% at that point.
And these are based on a change in the
expectancy
at that point in time. And so at that
point I obviously had 40% of the
position open. So I do the same thing.
Look at the potential outcomes move the
stop loss based on that and then
continue going. And in this case the the
price then reversed up hit the stop
loss. And therefore that was showing me
well beyond this point now it would have
been negative expectancy. So we're
getting out of the trade. Okay. So, it's
the same decisions at the points of
entry, but throughout the trade. And if
you want the full breakdown of this one,
like I mentioned, you'll get it in this
week's Nicholas's notes. There's just
something I quickly wanted to add here
that I missed the first time around that
I'm coming back to. There's a really
common incorrect statement that traders
make. It's like widespread. Lots of
traders are taught to do this. Lots of
traders do this as standard on every
single trade. And that is moving your
stop loss to break even once it starts
moving into a profit. And the thinking
here, the statement the traders think
they're making is that they now have a
risk-free trade, but the market doesn't
know about where you entered your trade.
I mean, technically, yes, it does, but
that's not really influencing where the
price goes and what the probabilities
are of the different outcomes. So if
we're entering a trade saying the
probability of this outcome and this
outcome makes it positive expectancy,
moving the stop loss to break even
before one of those outcomes has taken
place is reducing the probability of the
positive outcome because we're now
ruling out the possibility of this. So
whatever percentage probability we had
at the start when we were figuring out
if this is an opportunity has now
changed. It's not actually in line with
the calculation we had. So, for this
specific trade, yes, it's risk- free in
the sense that you're not going to end
up with a loss. But if we take a
thousand trades, and there are some that
could have been profitable that now end
up being break even, it can completely
change what the expected value is of all
of those trades that in the long run,
you might have taken an opportunity that
was positive expectancy and made it
negative expectancy. And if we think
about the statement that we're making,
if you took this trade where you've
moved your stop loss to break even and
you go and give it to that alien or
someone else that doesn't know what
you're thinking and say, "What statement
am I making?" Well, if they understand
the expectancy and that kind of thing,
they'll be saying something along the
lines of beyond that point is negative
expectancy. But that's not necessarily
the case because nothing has materially
changed since the point that you entered
the trade. So instead, you should only
be moving your stop loss to either break
even or somewhere else when that becomes
the tipping point beyond which your
trade would be in negative expectancy
territory because that's what's going to
lead to profitable results over the long
run. The problem a lot of traders have
is that they think about their trades as
individual things rather than thinking
about them in terms of probabilities,
which requires you to think about a
larger sample size. Look, I know that a
lot of what I've explained to you can
either come across as too complex for
the stage you're at right now, or maybe
there are certain things that I haven't
explained in a way that's clear enough
to you. I understand that that could be
the case. But rather than just
disregarding all of it and thinking, I'm
just going to stick with things that are
simple, try to get your head around it.
And if you have any questions where I
haven't explained something clearly
enough or maybe I've missed out
something, just ask me in the comment
section. I'll be happy to help. Because
if you can really click with this
concept and understand the use of it and
start aligning yourself with this and
the stuff we're going to discuss in the
next videos, I really believe that this
will set you on a better path for your
trading. And I know that in this
industry there's this race to
simplicity, but sometimes things do need
a certain amount of complexity. Just
enough complexity to do the job. And
trying to make everything as simple as
possible isn't necessarily going to lead
you to success. Sometimes things do need
to be a little bit more complicated. And
if you always avoid that and take the
path of least resistance and go for
what's easy, you're not necessarily
going to achieve your goals. So if you
can at least understand the underlying
message here and understand the concept
and start trying to think through your
trading and how it applies, it will set
you on a much better path. Same with the
next videos. And if it is a bit too
complicated, I'm sorry. I've tried my
best to make it as simple as I can. But
these things are tricky to explain. And
I've refilmed this many, many times, but
of course, some things are going to be
difficult to understand and some people
just won't click with it. But give it
your best shot. Re-watch it if you need
to. Ask questions if you need to. Don't
just give up on it and think, "Oh, he's
making things more complicated than
needed." I really mean what I say with
this, that this stuff is necessary to at
least be doing in principle. I mean, at
the end of the day, this is what trading
is all about. If you're going to
summarize what the skill of trading is,
it's the ability to analyze the markets,
to understand when you have some
advantage from a probabilities point of
view, and then to be able to express
that analysis in the correct way, making
the right statements through the actions
and decisions that you take. And
anything that overly standardizes things
by saying, I will do this this way in
every single case, all it's doing is not
reflecting the analysis correctly. And
vice versa, if you analyze everything in
exactly the same way every time, it's
just standardizing things so that the
statements you make through your
actions, even if you change them each
time, is not going to accurately reflect
that. So, it's about the skill of being
able to understand the situation and
then reflect that through your actions
and decisions. So, if you're avoiding
that because it doesn't sound simple
enough, then you're not really
developing the skill set that you need
to succeed. And that's what I'm trying
to get across to you is like there's a
certain level of complexity that's
necessary if you want to succeed here
when we get to what is actually at the
heart of what trading is all about. And
so just briefly I want to explain the
other two that are here. So obviously in
the case of this trade the exit point
was from a stop-loss hit. But if you
manually exit a trade what is the
statement that you're making? Well, if
entering a trade is that you have an
advantage above a base rate, exiting the
trade should be the opposite, that you
no longer have an advantage above the
base rate. Because if you did, maybe
you'd want to stay in that trade.
However, we also need to consider this
over here, which is the opportunity cost
of staying in a trade. And HBR is
holding period return. So, if we think
about the cruise liner example that
having your money held up there, you're
making a statement that this is the best
place for my money. It's the same when
you hold the trades beyond a certain
point. So it might be that you have the
initial part of the trade like let's say
you were entering here. You have the
initial part that's quite quick and
you've built up a profit maybe like 2%
or something and then it's like this for
a very long time and you're still
holding because you think eventually
there's more potential. But during all
of this period of time, let's call it
seven well in the markets be 5 days.
Could that money and that not
necessarily just the money but also your
mental focus and everything like that.
Could that have been given to a
different market where there's more
potential? So, the best way to think
about this is the holding period return.
If something's below a certain holding
period return, it's not worth your time.
Focus on markets that have a higher
holding period return. But again, I know
I've said this a couple of times. I'm
not intending to explain all of these in
full detail. Now, the whole point of
this was just to briefly walk you
through a few different statements that
are being made so that you understand
the concept. But if you want a full
explanation of these and other
statements that I made throughout the
process, let me know. But what I want to
do now is to move on to that next video
where we're going to talk about a mental
shift that's even more impactful and
even more important than what we've
discussed. Now, this one ties into that.
It's like we've laid the foundations and
now we're going to build upon that.
Because this next one, I believe, is
probably the main reason that most
traders end up failing. Because when you
understand what we'll discuss in that
next video, it changes the things that
you focus on to improve your trading, it
changes the sorts of actions you take,
the trading approaches that you choose
to use. It changes a whole lot of things
once you have that perspective shift.
And it's something I don't see very
often in this industry at the moment.